<source>

<component>Design Identification 32 bit</component>

<authors>
    <author login="beck">Patrik Beck</author>
</authors>

<description>
    Identification component is small component which is used to detect
    design inside FPGA. It contain project identification, design version,
    version of SW interface and string identification. Informations are
    stored inside registers which are accessible through dedicated 32 bit
    interface.
</description>

<interface>
	<!-- doplnit dividery -->
	<generic_map>
      <generic name="PROJECT_ID" type="std_logic_vector(15:0)" default="1">
          Project identification number. This number has to be unique for
          every project. There is no special policy how to assigne number
          for a new project.
      </generic>

      <generic name="SW_MAJOR" type="std_logic_vector(7:0)" default="1">
          Software interface version - major number. This number is
          incremented whenever new firmware design is released and the
          concept of software interface is changed (only big changes).
      </generic>

      <generic name="SW_MINOR" type="std_logic_vector(7:0)" default="1">
          Software interface version - minor number. This number is
          incremented whenever the software interface is changed (all
          changes). If SW major number is changed, the SW minor number is
          set to zero.
      </generic>

      <generic name="HW_MAJOR" type="std_logic_vector(15:0)" default="1">
          Firmware version - major number. This number is incremented only
          if new firmware version is released and the whole architecture is
          changed.
      </generic>

      <generic name="HW_MINOR" type="std_logic_vector(15:0)" default="1">
          Firmware version - minor number. This number is incremented
          whenever new firmware version is released. If HW major number is
          changed, the HW minor number is set to zero.
      </generic>

      <generic name="PROJECT_TEXT" type="std_logic_vector(255:0)" default="1">
          Project text - the project text is null terminated string which
          must not contain white spaces. Please use "_" character instead
          of spaces.
      </generic>
  </generic_map>

<port_map>
      <!-- Port map description -->
      <port name="CLK" dir="in" width="1">
          Component base clock. It has to be connected to the local bus
          clock.
      </port>

      <port name="RESET" dir="in" width="1">
          Global reset used for the first register.
      </port>

      <divider>Data Interface</divider>
      <port name="ADDRESS" dir="in" width="7">
          Internal register and ROM memory addressing.
      </port>

      <port name="DATA_IN" dir="in" width="32">
          Input data.
      </port>

      <port name="DATA_OUT" dir="in" width="32">
          Output data.
      </port>

      <port name="WRITE_ENABLE" dir="in" width="1">
          Signal enables writing data onto the addressed register.
      </port>

  </port_map>

</interface>

<constant> <!-- ### doplnit ### --> </constant>

<operations>
	<init>

		<it ref="### doplnit ###">Initialization is not necessary</it>

<!-- ### operace mohou byt poprehazovane ### -->

	</init>
<op name="Identification component detection" id="ID_COMP_DETECT">
        <p>
            Sometimes it is useful to have a way how to know if the
            identification component is presented in the design or not. So,
            the NEG register has been add at address 0 to ID component. If
            you write a value to the NEG register, the logic negation of
            the number is stored and can be also read. ID component should
            be placed to address 0 of FPGA address space. So, the NEG
            register should be also at address 0 of the whole FPGA address
            space.
        </p>
    </op>

<op name="Project detection" id="ID_PROJECT_DETECTION">
        <p>

            There are three identification types of identification in the
            ID component - project ID, SW version and HW version. You can
            have a look in address space description for detail
            informations.
        </p>

    </op>

<op name="Project string read" id="ID_PROJECT_STRING">
        <p>
            ID component contain also array of 16 bytes where text
            information about project is stored. The array is read
            only and contain ASCI values of given string. For more
            details see address space description.
        </p>
    </op>

</operations>

<addr_space id="ID" name="Design Identification" main="yes">
   <reg name="Negation register" id="ID_NEG" offset="0x0000" access="RW" words="1">
		<bit_vect bits="32">
			<description_above>
			<p>
         Sometimes it is usefull to have a way how to know if the
         identification component is presented in the design or not.
         So, the NEG register has been add at address 0 to ID
         component. If you write a value to the NEG register, the logic
         negation of the number is stored and can be also read. ID
         component should be placed to address 0 of FPGA address space.
         So, the NEG register should be also at address 0 of the whole
         FPGA address space.
		</p>
		<p>
		 Example: If you write 0x00000000 value to the ID_NEG register, then
		 0xFFFFFFFF value is stored and returned if read operation is performed.
		</p>

			</description_above>
		</bit_vect>
</reg>

	<reg name="Software version register" id="ID_SW_REG" offset="0x0004" access="R" words="1">
		<bit_vect bits="32">
			<description_above>
			This register is dedicated for SW. It consists of two parts.
           The first part contains project ID and the second design
           version.

			</description_above>
			<format>
      <bit from="0" to="7" name="SW minor version">
		  See documentation of interface - part generics for detailed
		  description and policy how to assign this number.
      </bit>
      <bit from="8" to="15" name="SW major version">
		  See documentation of interface - part generics for detailed
		  description and policy how to assign this number.
      </bit>
      <bit from="16" to="31" name="Project ID number">
		  See documentation of interface - part generics for detailed
		  description and policy how to assign this number.
      </bit>
   </format>
		</bit_vect>
</reg>

	<reg name="Hardware version register" id="ID_HW_REG" offset="0x0008" access="R" words="4">
		<bit_vect bits="32">
			<description_above>
			This register contain design version number which is exactly the same
		   as tag in CVS. Value in this registers should be used when any HW bug
		   is reported.

			</description_above>
			<format>
      <bit from="0" to="15" name="HW minor version">
		  See documentation of interface - part generics for detailed
		  description and policy how to assign this number.
      </bit>
      <bit from="16" to="31" name="HW major version">
		  See documentation of interface - part generics for detailed
		  description and policy how to assign this number.
      </bit>
   </format>
		</bit_vect>
</reg>

	<reg name="Identification" id="ID_TEXT" offset="0x0020" access="R" words="4">
		<bit_vect bits="32">
			<description_above>
			In this memory can be stored 16 bytes of text where any text can be
		   stored. For example SCAMPI or Liberouter. See documentation of
		   interface - part generics for detailed description and policy how to
		   assign this number.

			</description_above>
		</bit_vect>
</reg>

</addr_space>

<sw_body>
   <p>
   If the ID component is not present in the desing, driver support for
   the combo card is disabled(for example csbus won't work).
   </p>

   <p>
   To enable sw support without use of ID component the boot protection
   has to be disabled, when loading combo6core module. See
   documentation for combo6core for details.
</p>
</sw_body>

<body>

    <!-- Here is description in standard Satrapa format-->

    <h1>Identification component</h1>

    <p>
        ID component consists  of several register which are maped onto the
        FPGA address space and can be simple read.  The address space
        structure is shown on following picture.
    </p>

    <p>
       <obr src="fig/address_space.fig">Address space structure</obr>
    </p>

    <p>
        The first 32bit word is writable and is dedicated to detect if
        ID component is presented. If you write there any value, the
        negative value is stored.  Following 32bit register contain
        unique project number. Next two registers contain major and minor
        version number and the last 16 words is string for better project
        identification.
    </p>

    <p>
        Only the first ID detection register is writable. Other registers
        are read only.
    </p>

    <h2>Interface</h2>

    <p>

        ID interface behavior is similar to the memory interface. There is
        used independent data bus for in and out direction. One is used in
        read and the another one in write operation. Address bus is shared
        and additional DATA_WE signal enables write to registers.
    </p>
    <p>
        If entity ID_MI32 is used, memory interface is universal type t_mi32.
        In that case, four lowest bits are used for addressing and the rest
        is ignored.
    </p>

    <p>
        Read and write operations are shown on following picture. You can
        see that write operation is performed in only one clock cycles but
        the data latency in read operation is two clock cycles.
    </p>

    <h2>Block structure</h2>

    <p>
        The ID component structure is shown on following picture. ID
        consists of several register and address decoder. Registers are on
        the right side and on the left side, there is address decoder
        composed of several multiplexers.
    </p>

    <p>
       <obr src="fig/id.fig">Block structure</obr>
    </p>


</body>

</source>
